the world is going to have a new
monetary system in this decade that
we're in we're going to experience this
huge deflationary crash around the world
and people will just lose confidence in
currency and what do they always go back
to throughout history
time after time for the last 5000 years
actually they always go back to gold and
silver we are entering a period of
financial crisis that is the greatest
the world has ever known
the wealth transfer that will take place
during this decade is the greatest
wealth transfer in history wealth is
never destroyed it is merely transferred
and that means that on the opposite side
of every crisis there is an opportunity
the great news is that all you have to
do is to turn this crisis into your
great opportunity is to educate yourself
I believe that the best investment that
you can make in your lifetime is your
own education education on the history
of money education on Finance education
on how the global economy works
education on how all of these guys the
central bankers with stock market how
they can see you how they can scan you
if you learn what is going on and how
the financial world works you can put
yourself on the correct side of this
wealth transfer Winston Churchill once
said that the further you look into the
path the further you can see into the
future this program is all about
creating your own crystal ball being
able to gaze into the future being able
to change this crisis the greatest
crisis in the history of mankind into
your great opportunity
you
[Music]
so it all started back in 1999 when my
sister and I hired a financial planner
to help my mother with her assets and we
gave him control of the family's assets
and in the next year and a half he lost
50% of what she had you know he would
come to us every six months we'd have a
meeting and he'd have this smile on his
face just ear to ear smile ongoing we
did really well the SMP lost 24% and you
only lost 18 and so I fired him and I
moved all of her assets to cash and i
doand to studying the financial markets
which led me to into setting the economy
and when you start reading about the
global economy the people that are
concerned with trade deficits and budget
deficits it's the hard money advocates
the gold community and once I started
reading them they also write about
monetary history and then I really fell
in love because monetary history just
repeats and repeats over and over again
echoing all the way back to the
beginnings of civilization
[Music]
gold and silver have been the
predominant currencies for about five
thousand years but it wasn't until
somewhere between 680 BC and 630 bc's
that they became money that's when they
were minted into coins of equal weights
somewhere in lydia where each coin was
the same size and had the same weight
this made them interchangeable it's
called spongeable at that point they
became useful as a unit of account and a
measurement you could price a good or a
service in those gold or silver coins in
a certain number of them and it was
always the same for anybody whenever
they were buying that good or service
but it wasn't until they made their way
to the world's first free-market society
the prototype of democracy the cradle of
civilization Athens that they exploded
in use suddenly money found its natural
home the free markets
Athens was the first society to have a
working tax system and free markets this
enabled them to rise to the pinnacle of
civilization their prosperity allowed
them to create great works of art and
achieve a level of architecture and
engineering that the world had not yet
seen here we are 2,500 years later and
people are still in awe of their
achievements it was truly a fantastic
period in human history and the active
star shone brightly for many years so
this begs the question what went wrong
how did such a great and powerful
civilization fall the answer lies in the
same pattern that we see throughout
history too much greed and too much war
it was when the Athenians got involved
in the Peloponnesian wars a war with
Sparta that their monetary problems
began first they lost access to their
gold and silver mines they were also
paying armies that were on foot and they
were miles and miles away from happy so
as they pay their armies to buy goods
and services from the local populations
a deflation occurs in Athens because
they're sending all of their clients out
of the city then they started debasing
their Clinton's to pay for the war if
you take in a thousand coins in taxes
and then you melt those down those gold
coins and you mix 50% copper into your
gold
now you can mint 2000 coins so if you
take in only a thousand coins but you
spend two thousand coins what is that
called that is deficit spending
Athens began to do that during this war
with Sparta they also had these great
Public Works which were very expensive
and they finished the temple of Athena
Nike during the truth in the middle
there was a six year truth in the middle
of this 27 year war so they didn't stop
their great public works and allow their
market economy to heal from the expense
of this war as they debased their
coinage people would take the new
debased coins at face value at first
until there were a whole bunch of those
and there's something called Gresham's
law where people tend to save to keep
the thing that's rare and they spend the
thing that's common into circulation
first so all of the gold and silver
claims started to disappear from
circulation and become quite rare and it
was just these copper coins
suddenly it took a whole bunch of copper
coins to buy a gold or silver coin one
of those old gold or silver coins this
is the first time that gold or silver
ever had a price before that everything
was measured in a weight of gold and
silver so a large factor in Athens
downfall was the expense of war the
expansion of empire the debasement of
their currency the eventual inflation
that was caused
you know they mended these coins until
they became nothing but flexible copper
this was actually the world's first
hyperinflation and what it did was it
financially debilitated Athens to the
point where in 404 BC they surrendered
to Sparta and eventually they became
nothing but a satellite of Rome the
thing that amazes me is how history just
keeps on repeating and repeating and
repeating and we never learn from all of
our stupid mistakes we just repeat the
same stupid mistakes over and over and
over again today we are doing the same
thing that the Athenians did that caused
the loss of their great culture we're
doing the same currency debasement we're
doing the same deficit spending and it's
for the same reasons it's for war and
it's for great Public Works the
interesting thing about the
Peloponnesian War was how it started I
would say one of the interesting
parallels is that it started really with
Athens at its height and with a level of
hubris that set them down the road
towards ruin perhaps they felt that they
were
you know superior kanika mistakes a new
better exactly and they ended up
destroying the society as a result it's
a road that we're going down today right
I think absolutely yeah there was a play
written certainly after the token Asian
Wars about the worthlessness of the
copper flecks that are where their
coinage at the time so we go from gold
and silver very high-value money to a
currency that has a face value and it's
the first example that I can find in
history where a war was war and great
public works were being funded through
deficit spending what you've just seen
is the first recorded example of one of
the most predictable hidden secrets of
money the seven stages of Empire it's a
long-term cycle that echoes throughout
history right to this very day and is
basically a societal pendulum that
swings from quality money to quantity
currency and back again to quality money
it always plays out in seven stages it
always ends with gold delivering a
knockout blow to debased currencies and
it goes like this
Stage one the country starts out with
good money which is either gold or
silver or it's backed by gold or silver
stage two as it develops economically
and socially it begins to take on more
and more economic burdens adding layer
upon layer of Public Works stage three
as its economic affluence grows so does
its political influence and it increases
expenditures to fund a massive military
Stage four eventually it puts its
military to use and expenditures explode
stage-five to fund the war it steals the
wealth of its people by debasing their
coinage with base metals or by replacing
their money with currency that can be
created in unlimited quantities stage 6
the loss in purchasing power of the
expanded currency supply is sensed by
the population in the financial markets
triggering a loss of faith in the
currency stage 7 a mass movement out of
currency into precious metals and other
tangible assets takes place the currency
collapses and gold and silver rise in
price as they account for the huge
quantity of currency that was created
this process transfers massive wealth to
those who had the foresight to position
themselves beforehand in real money gold
and silver
you know our monetary system basically
steals from the poor and middle class
and transfers the wealth to the banks we
see this throughout history and it's
just repeating over and over again
what's happening in Greece right now is
basically the same thing that was
happening back in 407 BC the deficit
spending to fund all of these public
works and the debasement of their
currency supply caused them to become
nothing but a satellite of Rome today
they're becoming nothing but a satellite
of the banks
well the idea of Gresham's laws simply
that people are going to hold on to
what's value and spend what is valuable
way way back in my youth I was 11 years
old when went from a silver based
monetary system to a purely Fiat system
people saw that silver was money we got
used to it they didn't really think
about it and in 1965 under President
Johnson he basically said it was so much
too valuable to money we're going to
just start coming out these substitutes
which were what we call cupro-nickel
coins they were nickel or copper plated
with nickel time and of course the metal
value was far less and I understood as a
kid and yet very few adults really seem
to get the idea what was really going on
or a few and all it takes a few and of
course the bishop law took effect so the
currency came out of circulation rapidly
it's very interesting to me you know
knowing monetary history fairly well is
there always you know put out in silver
looking or gold looking form and in a
most cases you'll have a factory look
rather interesting and some of them are
like so we ran inside a school on the
outside with the look they have no value
at all really other than melt value of
pot now to me it's sort of subconscious
why are they making them gold colored
why they making them silver colored I
think there's an inherent knowledge in
the human specie that knows that gold
and silver have value so if they look in
their pocket may see something gold
colored or silver colored it makes it
didn't kind of a warm fuzzy feeling
that's like oh yeah you know but there's
no value in these coins
the next question is how does this
affect you my next stop was in London
where I'd been asked to give a
presentation to a group of businessmen
they wanted to understand the reason
that gold had surged recently and I
explained to them that to understand
gold you have to understand the monetary
history once you see where we've come
from you can get a much clearer
understanding of how the seven stages of
empire are playing out right now we
weren't allowed to show their faces but
we were allowed to film my presentation
so here it is the last hundred and forty
years of monetary history condensed in
just ten minutes
keep the seven stages of empire in mind
and as you watch this see if you can
recognize the signs everybody thinks the
US dollar still is gold and it hasn't
been since 1971 this is the world
monetary systems from 1873 when Germany
went on the classical gold standard
where each unit of currency is backed up
by an equivalent amount of gold in the
Treasury in the United States
$20 bill $20 gold piece in the vaults go
into any bank slap down your currency
which was a receipt for money a claim
check on money ask for your money gold
and silver and they would get it to you
so this shows this is currency this is
money otherwise there was no reason for
any government to store gold in their
vaults and then print this currency that
was backed by gold this is what gives
confidence in that and it gives
government's the ability to start this
scam in the first place where they print
these receipts for gold and then they
can print more of them than gold that
exists and that happened when we got to
World War one and all the combatant
stopped Redemption rights you could no
longer go on the bank and and trade your
Townsley remarks francs no longer
redeemable in gold and they lit up the
printing presses and started printing
like crazy then between the wars they
went on something called the Gold
Exchange standard where currencies would
be backed partially by gold so in the
United States under the Federal Reserve
Act of nineteen
teen week the Federal Reserve was
allowed to put $50 worth of claim checks
on gold currency and circulation
backed up by only $20 worth of gold so
with a 40% reserve ratio for every
twenty dollar gold piece in the vault
they could put $50 in circulation where
the dollars of the nation on trade we're
the big batch of dollars ever made oh we
used too much Familia probably much but
didn't and maybe we'll be present for
your dad then we get to 1944
now during both wars Europe paid the
u.s. with gold during World War one the
US didn't get into the war until the
very end of it we didn't really have
troops on the ground here in any
quantity until the last six months of
the war so for the first four years or
so we're selling you all of you know you
take all of your young men off of the
farms and turn them into soldiers you
take your factories that make posters
and they start making machine guns your
factories that made cars are now
building tanks and so you turn your
economy toward war and all of your
consumer goods and your grains had to be
imported from the United States and you
paid us with gold then in World War two
Hitler starts saber rattling in 1936
annexes Austria and 38 and invades
Poland in 39 Pearl Harbor wasn't until
the end of 1941 we didn't have troops on
the ground until I believe August of 42
so again there's like six years where
you're paying us with your gold and
we're selling you stuff this is where
Americans have this myth that war is
good for the economy or is good for the
economy if you're not in it and you're
selling them the tools of the trade
yes America's national income gets
bigger and bigger in 1943 it was a
hundred and forty two billion dollars
that was double the 1939 figures tripled
a figure for 1933 but by the end of
World War two the US had 2/3 of all the
world's monetary gold the central bank
gold
and the rest of the world had to share
the other third and Europe had none so
the world's monetary system was no
longer going to work it would collapse
but we had made all these loans of
dollars to Europe so Europe was flooded
with dollars and so representatives from
around the world met at Bretton Woods
New Hampshire in 1944 they come up with
a new world monetary system called the
Bretton Woods system where every
currency on the planet with the
exception of just a few they would be
backed by the US dollar and the US
dollar would then be backed by gold at
$35 per ounce this gave confidence to
all currencies so this gave the world
stability and it pegged all the world's
currencies to each other through the
dollar to gold so there was no such
thing as the Forex currencies didn't
float the exchange rates were fixed year
after year and this helped to make world
trade boom then the dollar standard
starts because we kept on printing
dollars under the Bretton Woods system
there there was no reserve ratio
established where the US actually had to
have a certain amount of gold for how
many dollars we created so we had done a
bunch of deficit spending for Korea for
Vietnam for Johnson's Great Society and
expanded the currency supply the amount
of paper dollars in circulation and
exported them all over the world and
then in the 60s Charles DeGaulle
president of France realizes that we
don't have the goal to back up the
dollars respectable food itself except
autocracy vidura woman sister to the law
fan please America acidity is oddities
God is not in the hilly country Cal
secure he was released a a big big Allah
to check a résumé
yes non SSA realization Internacional
Swati WMC Toluca as a legal milord more
[Music]
service Bosman str indisputable Aquino
Fattah Lana you can't be all
particularly chaos of Vientiane the
guapa
he's busy Avila hey Elmo looks iike the
fellow Oh to Google and he starts asking
France ax asks for their gold and trade
in dollars and at that point other
countries saw this and start jumping on
board and the u.s. lost 50% of its gold
from 1959 to 1971 but we still had in 71
about 12 times more dollars that we had
created than there was gold and this run
on the bank basically the u.s. now being
the bank this is a giant worldwide bank
run because the US for the second time
had committed a fraud and created more
receipts for gold than there was gold
it's that simple then finally the
markets sort of sense this and Nixon was
forced to take us off the gold standard
because if he had paid out gold until it
got to zero
once we couldn't pay on some of those
dollars the entire worldwide monetary
system would have collapsed I have
directed secretary Connolly to suspend
temporarily the convertibility of the
dollar into gold or other reserve assets
except in amounts and conditions
determined to be in the interest of
monetary stability and in the best
interest of the United States and full
cooperation with the International
Monetary Fund and those who trade with
us we will press for the necessary
reforms to set up an urgent lee needed
new international monetary system and on
August 15th 1971 all the world's
currencies became fiat currency I don't
know why the rest of the world didn't
rush out and hang him
but but they didn't they just all went
along with this to our friends abroad I
give this assurance the United States
has always been and will continue to be
a forward-looking and trustworthy
trading partner there have been
thousands upon thousands upon thousands
of fiat currencies throughout history
and there isn't one that survived it is
a 100 percent failure rate and we
started this experiment where all the
world's currencies would be fiat
currencies simultaneously in 1971 but
what we have here 30 to 40 years
different monetary system 30 years 28
years 39 years plus what's next the
world is going to have a new monetary
system in this decade that we're in
we're going to experience this huge
deflationary crash around the world the
world will probably end up on some sort
of new monetary system probably after
governments try and print their way out
of this and cause hyperinflations of all
the currencies and people will just lose
confidence in currency and what do they
always go back to throughout history
time after time for the last 5,000 years
actually they always go back to gold and
silver in a world of floating currencies
and that's what all national currencies
are today they bob up and down relative
to each other but they're all syncing
relative to gold that includes the
dollar as well as the euro and the
British Pound and all the others they're
going to continue to lose value continue
to lose purchasing power
personally I don't think there's any way
of avoiding what is coming there's no
way to fix it right now there's only a
way to either let it wipe you out or to
benefit from it and I want to make sure
that it's not just all it's not just a
few of the big investors in the world
that are ending up with all the cookies
I want to make sure that there's as many
small investors as possible that are
benefiting from it because that's what
makes society run middle-class small
investor one of the biggest challenges
for human veins is that physiologically
we are designed to operate in recency
now the fight or flight response is
literally in my cells literally and so
that when I'm in the wild it's about I
need to look for some to eat or make
sure I don't get even and how that
translates into the model world is that
we think only about what's happening
immediately in front of us so we think a
long time is last week in the world of
YouTube and Facebook and instant
messaging we think three seconds is a
long time like did you get the poster I
already posted it and the reality is
that you look at history and I don't
mean a week I don't mean a month
I mean decades I mean 100 years I mean a
couple of hundred years I mean more than
a couple reviews because that's a season
patent you can see some things that are
going on because he should repeats
itself there are some trends and there's
some movements that you can learn from
and you would only have to go outside of
your your human instincts to local
history because we just want to focus on
right now because I said that's about
either eating or being able so we're
going to go beyond that and that means
not just focusing on the hair now but
learning some real powerful stuff and
what's happened because there just might
be some indicated there is what's gonna
happen the future
now the seven stages of empire just as a
reminder started with sound money and
then a country adds layers of Public
Works and social programs and then
develops a massive military and then
puts that military to use and to pay for
the war it debases its currency supply
which causes a loss of faith in the
currency which then leads to a currency
crisis and gold does an accounting of
the expansion of that fiat currency
supply that happened over all those
years of the first five stages we are in
the sixth at beginning the seventh stage
gold started the accounting in the year
2001 it was 250 dollars then but we're
still in the very early stages of this
well that's right I think one of the
problems with gold is people just don't
understand it I mean for one thing it's
sort of been banished from the
curriculum for 35 years we have going on
two generations of academics and
scholars who have never studied gold
unless you're specialists in economic
history and go back and look at it now
when I was in University and even when I
was in graduate school in economics we
were still on the gold standard in some
form it was fairly attenuated but when
you when you studied the IMF and you
looked at how they present the finances
of a country and they break down the
reserves and you know the capital
accounts gold was a line item in the
capital account you had to understand
how it what role had played and how it
you know could equilibrate in terms of
balance of trade
well that's gone the IMF Nixon went off
the gold standard 1971 and bright young
economic students just don't understand
gold they think it's a joke or they
think it's maybe a commodity trader
momentum trade they don't understand
that it really is money parks loss
so now we've learned that money was born
in roughly 630 BC when it became
fungible it was free markets and sound
money that led to Athens great
prosperity but the basement of their
money for deficit spending on war and
Public Works played a large role in
their demise over the past 140 years
we've based our own currencies to the
point where two generations of scholars
don't even understand gold we learned
about Gresham's law and that bad money
drives out good in recent history there
has been a new monetary system roughly
every 40 years and we've learned that we
are in the sixth stage of the seven
stages of empire so that's it for this
episode
join us next time when we learn more
about the chaotic state of the u.s.
dollar standard and how it's going to
affect you no matter where you live on
the planet when I wrote my book I said
that we're coming into an era that is
going to be the greatest wealth transfer
in the history of mankind therefore it's
the greatest opportunity in the history
of mankind I've made it my mission to
help as many people as possible get
through this crisis and to come out on
the best side of the wealth transfer
I've just finished filming an exclusive
presentation titled how the seventh
stage will unfold where I detail what
I'm doing personally to prepare for a
range of scenarios it's available at
hidden secrets of money calm as part of
your free information toolkit so my
challenge to you for this episode is to
try and find a single example in all of
monetary history of a crisis that was
brought on by too much deficit spending
too much debt and too much currency
debasement being solved by more deficit
spending more debt and more currency
debasement until then good luck and I'll
see you at the bonus presentation at
hidden secrets of money calm thanks
you bet there's no other there is no
other side you either silver and gold or
your doing
that's exactly the way the world is
always working out the way it's working
right now turn on television watch with
the price of gold because a dollar going
down gold going up silvers going up
that's exactly the way it's always
working it's always work that way is
working that way now and why is anyone
surprised why is it surprised it's
always work what a thousand years with a
rose work exactly that way it's
happening that way now they're cool
living weird beyond where Mike Maloney's
hidden secrets of money is made possible
by the clients of gold silver calm your
continued loyalty and support allows us
to educate the public on how to both
protect themselves and benefit in the
turbulent times ahead - all gold silver
calm customers thank you hidden secrets
of money would not be possible without
you